Hello, I'm William
Zaloga, and this is a
presentation on the
pathology of dilated and
hypertrophic
cardiomyopathies. Here is my
contact information
shown on this slide.
These are the objectives.
Both dilated and
hypertrophic cardiomyopathies
will start with general
characteristics,
then more details of
the etiology, diagnosis,
management, things
like that for both.
At the end of dilated
cardiomyopathy, a related
disorder is arrhythmogenic
right matricular
cardiomyopathy. That will
be discussed briefly.
And I will provide summaries
so you can compare and
contrast dilated and
hypertrophic cardiomyopathies.
Cardiomyopathies are
heart muscle diseases.
So they're generally
going to be structural
abnormalities that will
impair myocardial performance.
They are distinct
from cardiovascular
diseases like hypertension
or valve disorders
because they are diseases
of the muscle itself.
often the cause is unknown
or known as idiopathic so
what you'll see clinically
is going to be signs of
heart failure including
shortness of breath fatigue
and swelling of the extremities
and that's caused by
fluid buildup you can also
see shortness of breath
because of pulmonary fluid
buildup so they can this
can develop slowly or start
suddenly depending on what
kind of cardiomyopathy is
affecting your patients.
So there's primary
and secondary types.
Primary types mainly
involve the heart itself.
Those are genetic or acquired.
For example, acquired
can be an infection like viral
infection or chemotherapy
or genes can be mutated and
cause protein contraction
protein abnormalities,
cell contact abnormalities,
cytoskeletal abnormalities.
If there are ion
transport in the cell membrane,
you can get dysrhythmias.
Secondary ones are a part
of some multi-organ disease
the patient has like
hemochromatosis and amyloidosis.
So it's going to be a
component of that. These
are both restrictive
cardiomyopathies, which are
in the other lecture that
I do on cardiomyopathies.
The types we're
discussing here, and
on these two lectures I do for
Cardiomyopathy, are
seen in the diagram.
And some description
is here. Dilated
is going to be
90% of the cases.
So as the name implies,
there's going to be
dilation, and that's going
to be of the ventricles.
and these enlarged
ventricles will lead to a
contraction dysfunction
because they're so large there
will be so much fluid in
there and the heart is thin
damaged and weakened that
it cannot pump all that
fluid out so as a result
you can see the left atria
there might be some regurg
and stretching or the
left atria or the pressure
will be too high because
a lot of that residual
volume that the atrial won't
completely empty and that
will begin to stretch.
And this will include
arrhythmogenic cardiomyopathy,
which primarily affects the
right side of the heart.
So, it can only be one side
of the heart sometimes.
But this one's rare,
arrhythmogenic.
Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy,
the heart ventricles
are abnormally thickened.
It can be one side, it can
be the septum, it can be
both sides as is shown
here. and because of the
pressure and then the blood
can't get into it because
it's thickened and stiff,
it's going to be a diastolic
relaxation dysfunction.
The pressure is going
to build up here in the
left ventricle but also
on the left atria too.
Restrictive
cardiomyopathy is also a
diet as shown here
on the lower right.
The heart ventricles look
like they're not that
structurally different from
normal but it's a diastolic
dysfunction because these
ventricles are infiltrated
by something that's
making them stiff and non
-compliant and that's the
least frequent one too.
So we'll start with
dilated. As you can see
in the image, the heart
will be globoid or
rounded and flabby and
poorly contractile.
In the images below, these
are cross sections of
the ventricles. You'll see
the ventricle on the left
shows normal and on the
right shows dilated and
thinned ventricles and
even the septum 2 and some
changes within the myocardium
due to the damage caused
by whatever the entity
is that's causing that.
The hypertrophy, there is
hypertrophy because you
have more myocardium
here because it's dilated
and stretched than you would
see in the normal heart.
That's because the new
sarcomeres are going to
be added in series with
that dilation. That's
known as eccentric hypertrophy.
The scientists named
it that way. It's
eccentric. And that's in the
dilated and one with the
contractile dysfunction.
Versus pressure overload
type of systemic disorders
like hypertension, where
the sarcomeres are going
to be added to new existing
sarcomeres in parallel.
that's going to produce
concentric hypertrophy.
You're usually with
dilated going to see all
four chambers enlarged and
you can get an idea that
this is occurring but
you'll it'll be more
obvious as you approach
end-stage disease but there
can be subtle signs
early. It's suggested by
the left ventricular
ejection fraction being
below 40 percent, no more
than 50 to 70 percent.
Remember that the
right heart can be
affected by the
left heart failure,
so biventricular
failure can result.
When you look under the
microscope at a biopsy,
you're going to
see fibrosis in the
interstitium. This is a
trichrome stain shown on
the right, and fibrosis
will appear as blue.
The nuclei will be
black and the cytoplasm
itself will be a
brick red or pink.
The myocytes are going to
be enlarged and they're
going to be there's going
to be irregular hypertrophy
so some of them are
going to be small some of
them are going to be very
large and irregular and
this one's large and it
looks like there's some
fissures in it and you're
going to see some vacuoles
and some of them that's
due to the myocyte damage.
The severity of this that
you see under the microscope
doesn't agree with the
amount of dysfunction
or the prognosis, but it
can indicate the cause.
Next is a good diagram that
discusses the pathophysiology.
What's going to occur initially
with DCM is the stroke
volume and the cardiac output
are going to be decreased
and because of that
there's going to be three
compensatory effects that
are going to occur and so we
go we follow the flow
diagram here and we get this
frank starling effect and
this is the heart trying to
protect itself from this
dilated cardiomyopathy effect
so the end diastolic
volume is going to increase
there's going to be stretch
and that's going to increase
the force of contraction
that's the frank starling
effect and that's going to
try increase stroke volume.
You're going to get neurohormonal
activation and that's
going to increase the heart
rate and that'll try to
help to increase the cardiac
output. But the decreased
cardiac output that instigated
that is going to activate
the RAS system. So you're
going to get angiotensin
to analdosterone which is
going to increase systemic
vascular resistance and
intervascular volume which are
going to worsen your
cardiomyopathy and the dilation.
And I already talked about
some of these effects but
I put a little bit more
in here the patient could
be asymptomatic early on
but eventually heart failure
will develop if nothing's
done okay with angiotensin
II the systemic vascular
resistance is going to be
increased so the afterlone
is going to be just become
too high and that's going
to worsen your already
impaired left ventricle
with aldosterone fluid is
going to back up and that's
going to cause congestion.
If it's pulmonary, that's
going to be involving the
left heart being dilated,
and if it's systemic,
that's going to involve the
right heart being dilated.
If this occurs in chronic
elevations of albostrone,
albostrone, nothing's done,
of albostrone angiotensin
II occur, then remodeling
and fibrosis will develop.
As I biopsy of the myocardium.
When the heart and lars,
there's going to be
structural abnormalities that
can occur not only in the
ventricles and the
myocardium, but in the atria,
as I discussed already,
but also in the valves too.
Microlonic tricuspid
regurgitation can occur.
So regurgitation into the
left atria will decrease
the stroke volume during
systole and that will result
to increased volume and
pressure overload so the atria
can dilate and if that
happens that can cause atrial
fibrillation and thrombus
formation may occur too.
If the recurrent volume
then returns to the left
ventricle that was in the
atria and each diastole
the volume gets greater
and stretches it out more
so heart failure
starts to develop.
Clinically you'll
see slow progressive
So, let's distinguish
it from other ones.
Signs and symptoms
of CHF, that's DCM.
Signs will include cool
extremities, low
artery pressure,
tachycardia, if it's involving
pulmonary condition, crackles,
and the heart's large, so
that we have a displaced
PMI, and there'll be a third
heart sound. And that's
due to, well, I write why
that's here. The third
heart sound is a characteristic
of heart failure.
That third heart sound can be
normal in young
people and athletes,
but abnormal in
older results and
indicates systolic
heart failure.
These are some of the
complications that
I've already talked
about, and the mortality
is high from progressive
failure or the
dysrhythmias that can
be associated with that.
so general categories of
DCM these are going to be
the causes and I put this
asterisk by the ones that
are potentially reversible
and that's important because
there's something you
can do about it and that
will potentially protect
them from going into heart
failure if it's caught
early so idiopathic is going
to be the most common but
also genetic is a category
Infections and inflammation can
cause this disorder as well.
Toxins can do that.
Alcohol is a common one. So
is drugs, and chemotherapy
is a well-known one.
But there's systemic metabolic
disorders that can
produce that as well,
and also neuromuscular
disorders,
dystrophies themselves
of the muscle.
okay here's just some of
the categories that are
associated with the ones we
just went over so peripartum
associated okay and
peripartum associated is going
to be sort of in that
idiopathic category it's going
to occur late pregnancy
or post shortly postpartum
and it can occur in another
pregnancy. It's probably
multifactorial, poorly
understood why it occurs.
Here's some guesses
why scientists
think it might be occurring.
50% of these people
after their postpartum
period will regain
normal function.
But the risks increase with
increased age of the mother,
African-American race, and if a
mother has multiple gestations.
Genetic health is
another category.
Familial characteristics
are going to be noted
in about 30 to 50 percent
of cases, and autosomal
dominant inheritance
is going to be the most
kind of inheritance
pattern that will occur.
And the most common
mutation noted is going to
be a mutation of this
gene which encodes titan,
which is one of the
protein filaments within
the sarcomators that
helps with contraction.
And that's going to count
for about 20% of the cases.
Less commonly, it's
going to be autosomal
recessive, X-linked,
and mitochondrial.
There's an X-linked form
that's linked to the gene
for dystrophin. So you get
muscular dystrophy type
signs in early puberty or
after puberty or early as an
early adult. You can
have problems with the
mitochondrial genes, and those
typically involve children.
The pathogenesis of DCM,
again, we're going to
another category. This is
the infection category.
With the infections, that's
known as myocarditis,
the heart can
appear normal or be
dilated. In advanced
stages, it can produce the
myrothrombi because of
inflammatory effects.
And this diagram shows normal
myocytes here and their fibers.
So these are cardiomyocytes.
So you see the
insensitium, but you
also see these little
blue dots. Those are
inflammatory cells.
So interstitial inflammatory
infiltrate as seen here.
Mostly lymphocytes in this
H&E state slide of the
myocardium. And here are
damaged myocytes, you see how
they're fragmented, they're
not as eosinophilic anymore,
and the mortars are ragged
and irregular, and you
can see more of that that's
scattered throughout.
So the virus can have
a direct cytopathic
effect as well as
the lymphocytes too,
through their inflammatory
cytokines, and because
the inflammation fibrosis
may occur, and that
will also affect the
contraction of the
myocardium. Some people
fully recover but others go
on to DCM and possible
heart failure and death.
Some non-viral causes
but still infectious I
list here such as Chagas
disease 10% died from
that and that's associated
with trypanosomes.
And cardiac insufficiency
can occur much later in life,
okay?
Trichinosis is another
common one that's due
to a helminth that
invades the myocardium.
Toxoplasma does the same.
Lyon disease, Borrelia,
does the same. And so
does coronibacterium,
which produces diphtheria.
Non-infectious causes
which cause inflammation
are hypersensitivity
varieties and there if you
do a biopsy you'll see
a large proportion of
eosinophils along with
lymphocytes and macrophages.
But there will be a lot
of eosinophils which
will tell you that it
could be hypersensitivity.
There's a giant cell
myocarditis which will show a
lot of giant cells and
they'll be multi-nucleated
and that'll be part of the
inflammatory infiltrate
along with a lot of other
leukocytes. leukocytes.
It has a poor prognosis
and you'll see necrosis
in here just like here
where you have necrotic
cardiomyocytes. Another
category is toxin induced.
One of the most strongly
associated is excessive
alcohol use and it's the
metabolite acetaldehyde
which has a direct
toxin to the myocardium.
And here's a shows the
pathogenesis of how that
occurs and shows how
cell function declines.
Chronic alcoholism can
also produce beriberi which
is a thiamine deficiency
and beriberi heart disease
indistinguishable from
dilated cardiomyopathy.
This can be reversible
obviously abstinence
from alcohol and
ventricular function can
improve. Other toxins,
known toxins, are
chemotherapy drugs,
adriamycin, elysium, cocaine,
cobalt, iron,
hemochromatosis,
for example, if
you get a lot of transfusions.
Also there's an
unusual one category
of super physiologic stress.
What is going on there is
scientists think that there's
catecholamine toxicity
that is occurring. It can
occur during persistent
tachycardia, hyperthyroidism,
pheochromocytomas, cocaine use,
vasopressors like dopamine,
and what you'll see
is what's called contraction
band necrosis, okay,
because of hypercontractility,
which will take
the sarcomere proteins
and smush them together
so you get these bands
that are perpendicular
to the long axis of
the cardiomyocytes.
Okay, with intense
autonomic stimulation, which
can occur during emotional
distress or intracranial
lesions, there's something
that Dr. Takotsubo
discovered, and Takotsubo
refers to octopus
pot because the heart
kind of looked like that,
which is a Takotsubo
cardiomyopathy
known as heartbreak syndrome.
So left ventricle
cardiac dysfunction, left
ventricle becomes
dysfunctional, And that
follows extreme
psychological stress or
heartbreak, as it's
colloquially known as.
So it's most prominent
at the apex, so you'll
see apical ballooning.
And the mechanism
is uncertain, but could
be calcium overload
from this catecholamine
toxicity and focal
basal constriction,
contraction band necrosis.
Treatments. Try to
treat it early and treat
the underlying cause,
if you know it. and
provide symptom relief,
for example, if they're
having trouble breathing,
and with edema,
and decrease the
congestion, increase
the cardiac output if you can,
prevent complications like
thrombi, thrombocoholic events,
treat any dysrhythmias, and
that'll help them survive.
So some standard
treatments I list
here, like ACE
inhibitors, beta blockers,
diuretics, digoxin,
those are meds.
Amiodarone is used for people
at high risk for worsening
heart failure because
amiodarone doesn't affect
the heart function as much
as all these other ones.
Anticoagulation for those
prone to thrombus forming.
An implantable cardioverter
defibrillator for
those to prevent some
cardiac death if there's
a dangerous heart
rhythm that is detected.
Cardiac transplantation
may be the only definitive
treatment, But if a
person needs a transplant
and they don't get it,
then the survival is poor.
A third of these patients,
believe it or not, spontaneously
improve after their
diagnosis. Maybe they do
something, exercise something
that helps them improve.
Or they just do
it spontaneously.
Maybe there was an underlying
unknown condition that
occurs and then resolved
as their body resolved it.
Here's a summary that
is good. It's a flow
chart to follow. shows that
contractility decreases
and what increases and
the signs and symptoms
that you'll see and
the effects it can have
on other structures
besides the myocardium.
Here's a summary that
goes over genetic and non
-genetic causes and some
of the signs and symptoms
that you'll see. It's
very brief so you just
look at it if you want
this review real quickly.
Okay,
arrhythmogenic right
ventricular cardiomyopathy
also known as
arrhythmogenic right
ventricular dysplasia and
it's rare it's progressive
mostly sporadic but some
familiar forms do occur and
so something has been learned
because of that what they
learned is that there's
autosomal dominant inheritance
and there's deletion
of cardiac myocyte cell
membrane desmosome proteins
okay and I don't know I put
two arrows here I guess I
forgot to delete one but that
will lead to fibrosis and
fatty replacements okay
and the next slide will show
you what that looks like.
So there'll be, or a
barren signaling, depending
on what part of the
myocardium. Maybe it's
affecting the conduction
system or just the spread
of the action potential
through the ventricle.
It's going to lead to
right ventricle failure,
maybe rhythm disturbances.
Because of these
disturbances, such as
ventricular tachycardia,
fibrillation, sudden
death may occur.
There's going to be
abnormal right ventricle
morphology or structure
when imaging is done.
Treatment usually
involves the ICD to be
implanted and there's a
syndrome associated with
hyperkeratosis called
Naxosyndrome and they
discovered imitation in
the placoglobin gene.
If you do an EKG you'll
see a possible Epsilon wave
which is going to be an
unusual notch at the end
of the QRS complex so here's
the QRS and it's supposed
to go up and down and
back over here but instead
you got a notch okay so
that in case abnormal RV
activation and that's known
as the Epsilon wave and
that's going to be a seen
best in v1 lead and this is
going to be an inverted t
wave in v1 through v3 so
that's abnormal conduction
that can be picked up on an
ekg so look for the epsilon
light for that can be ercb
and then i put this uh
line around this red
line around the part of
the heart that's affected
you see a lot of x see
here's the left ventricle
this is the cross
section of the ventricles
You'll see how this is
massively dilated right
ventricles, bigger than
the left ventricle.
You'll see there's some
fibrosis. It's going to be
these pale tan areas. But
this area here, you don't
even see a lot of this tan
brown heart muscle. You
see a little bit here,
maybe a little bit here, but
this looks like it's mostly
fibrous tissue and fat.
And if you do an H&E stain
tissue section of this,
here's the myocardium, and
this is a trichrome stain.
And the fibrous tissue
shows up blue, and
here it's just all
fibrous tissue. You
don't see any myocardium
in a lot of fat,
okay?
So you get severe right
ventricular thinning
and dilation.
Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy,
also known as idiopathic
hypertrophic stub
aortic stenosis,
has a relatively
common incidence,
one in 500 births worldwide.
What you have here is
a poorly compliant left
ventricle versus a dilated
and flabby one that you
see in dilated
cardiomyopathy. So it's poorly
compliant. That leads to
abnormal diastolic filling.
There also can be intermittent
obstruction because
myocardium is hypertrophic,
and so that disturbs
the structure, and
it's not going to, the
volume is going to be
decreased, and it's going to
affect the valve structure
and things like that,
and that can
produce a functional
obstruction of the
outflow tract from the
left ventricle or
the right ventricle.
So it's going to be a diastolic
dysfunction, systolic is okay.
So in the absence of an
external stimuli, you're
going to have unexplained
left ventricular
hypertrophy and the cause
of it is going to be a
disease of the sarcomere
proteins so it's a massive
primary so that's primarily
just the myocardium
hypertrophy without dilation
so you're going to have
this greatly increased
muscle mass and the blood
vessels can't get enough blood
to it to support it so and
so they're going to
struggle and degrade and so
you're going to have decreased
outflow and obstruction.
And that will lead to
myocardial ischemia also because
these coronary arteries
passing through that
hypertrophic really tightly
squeezing myocardium is also
squeezing those vessels
and hardening their walls.
So it's hypercontracting versus
the Flavia DCM I
already mentioned.
The cause, about 75%
familial autosomal dominant
inheritance. Hundreds
of mutations have been
discovered and those are
of sarcomere proteins.
Most are point mutations
in nine different genes,
beta myosin heavy chain protein
is the most commonly affected.
It is associated with
Friedrich's ataxia, which
can lead to severe heart
complications, so it can
be part of a systemic
disorder, which is Friedrich's
is also a genetic disorder
of the mitochondria.
So sequence of events
that lead to the disease
is poorly understood and
the prognosis varies,
but it does correlate with
which mutation you do have.
Here's a little bit
of the normal and the
disease contraction
mechanisms of the heart.
Normal sarcomeric
contraction is shown in the
diagram described here above
the diagram on the left.
Calcium-troponin-actin
-myosin interactions
will occur as long as
well as the ATPase that
causes a straight change
in conformation of the
myosin head and that
moves the actin along.
With disease, there's a
mutated protein somewhere and
this diagram does show in
these red spots you know
where some mutation where
some mutations may occur
there's hundreds of them so
in the neck and the head here
on tropomyosin here on
troponin C so all over the
place and these are just a
few so there's going to be
within the sarcomere so it'll
be contractile impairments
and increased myocyte
stress that's going to lead
to hypercarphe of those
myocytes due to growth factor
release and fibroblast
proliferation okay and that's
also due to growth factor
release as well but this
growth factor release
doesn't lead to an orderly
production of new myofibers,
due to the contractile
impairments and injury that's
increasing myocyte stress,
it just leads to disarray
and because of this
disarray and injury
with growth factors
and increased stress
due to damaged myocytes,
you'll get interstitial
fibrosis as well,
which will also contribute
to the stiffness.
Okay, so you see here,
normal heart
bisected on the left
and hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy.
You do notice that the
septum here is very
hypertrophied. The free wall
is somewhat hypertrophied
and usually in this
condition right here where it
has the left ventricle
affected, the septum is
going to be more hypertrophied
than the free wall.
And you'll end up, instead
of the cavity shown here,
with a smaller restricted
banana-like shape and there's
going to be protrusion of
the septum that's going
to affect this valve right
here. So the mitral valve
is also going to be affected
and that can produce
an obstruction of the left
ventricular outflow tract.
You can see an endocardial
plaque due to the fibrosis,
due to thickening of that
leaflet on the mitral valve
and here's an example I
got another H&E stain slide
on the next slide so this
shows the fibers well the
fibers are going to be stiff
and that's going to lead
to diastolic failure but here
in this H&E stain section
you're going to see pink
areas of collagen okay that
are increased and the
myocytes are supposed to be
cardiomyocytes are supposed
to be an interstitium and
they're traveling more or
less perpendicular with each
other but here you see some
you know going down this
direction some going up in
this direction more going
down in this direction so
there's disarray and increased
fibrosis here shows a little
more that the disarray
as cardiomyocytes are binding
to other cardiomyocytes
that are parallel to them,
instead of end-on-end.
And you see the
hypertrophy, CDMRs, and
irregular nuclei of
these cells, and these
myofibras are going to
be thickened as well.
So myocyte hypertrophy,
fibrosis, disarray,
remember the disarray, and
fibrosis, if it involves
the conduction system,
you can get dysrhythmias.
So, you can have obstruction
or no obstruction,
that refers to the outflow
tract from the heart.
So without obstruction,
the diastolic pressures
are going to increase
because of that decreased
volume and thick myocardium,
and that's going to be
transmitted back to the
left atria and the pulmonary
vessels, so you get
congestion in the lungs.
With obstruction, and
this is a dynamic type of
obstruction, so during systole,
there's to be an obstruction
and here's the flow diagram
that shows you know what
happens but it's going
to lead to a transient
obstruction of the left
ventricular outflow tract i only
have some diagrams that kind
of show that here um here's
um the septum and the aorta
as they would uh be in
someone with this condition
and the septum i guess
they didn't make it as thick
as it normally but this is
going to be thickened.
You have septal subaortic
hypertrophy and then you get
functional aortic stenosis.
This is because with
systole as the thickened
and hypercontractile
ventricle contract,
this valve comes open
and stuck against
this protruding
subaortic septum.
Okay,
so some of that blood
will go back into the left
atria due to mitral
regurgitation and because this is
dilated now, fibrillation
can occur of the atria.
So here's another
example of what's called
asymmetric septal
hypergraphy. Okay,
so the septum is dilated
down here and there will
be The systolic anterior
motion, that's what SAM
is, of this anterior
leaflet of the mitral valve.
And that will lead
to obstruction
of left ventricular
output tract.
Maybe mitral
regurgitation as well.
Both of these have
pressure gradient
increases that will
increase wall stress
and produce angina
due to focal ischemia,
dyspnea, and possible syncope.
Here
is a flow diagram,
summary, which shows
how the different
structural abnormalities
of the heart produce
signs and symptoms.
MbO2 is the myocardial oxygen
consumption, so
that's increased.
But you'll have myocyte
hypergraphy, LVH,
and that could lead
to angina and dyspnea.
Disarray can lead
to arrhythmias,
sudden death, syncope.
This obstruction of the
outflow tract contributes
to the angina, and
micro-regerge, that will
produce dyspnea, and
cardiac output won't be
increased with exertion.
You have that functional
obstruction, remember.
so syncope can occur.
Clinically, you have
no physical limitations
to extensive
limitation. It varies.
Most don't have a severe
outlaw obstruction.
Most symptoms result
from impairment of
diastolic filling, as
we've already discussed.
Some Problems and
complications you can find are
mitral regurgs, you might
hear a murmur, fibrillation,
you can have thrombus
form, or you can get
really serious and go
into cardiac failure,
ventricular arrhythmias,
syncope, and sudden death.
It's the most common
cardiac abnormality in young
athletes who die suddenly
due to severe exertion,
and that's commonly due to
ventricular arrhythmias.
So, risk factors are if
a patient has a history
of sycopy, a family
history of sudden death,
or if they're at a high
risk of mutation from
their family history, or
extreme hypertrophy if
you do a study and find
the lip ventricle is
really thick and that
correlates with the risk.
So here's some
clinical features. This
is a diagram that
shows the flow charts,
flow diagrams of hypertrophy
itself, what effects it can
occur, how the effects occur.
Some of the effects include
dyspnea, angina, light
hedonism, syncope, and
arrhythmias, and these are how
those occur. You know, heart
mass increases, O2 demand
increases, and you know how
syncope occurs down here,
arrhythmia can
worsen hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy symptoms
like AFib can occur
because of loss and
the atrial kick,
so diastolic feeling
is further impaired
and you get worse
pulmonary congestion.
If you have this
plus obstruction,
then the mechanisms that
are included will be
increased systolic ventricular
pressures obstruction,
then that microregurge
might become a problem.
For the angina, you'll have
increased myocardial
oxygen demand.
For lightheadedness,
here's a flow
diagram that shows
you'll have decreased
cardiac output and
cerebral perfusion.
And syncope, with
physical exertion,
you'll have that
obstruction, so you'll have
decreased cardiac
output and syncope.
So here's a pathophysiology
summary diagram
shown here. Kind of
shows the same things
as any other diagram
except this is simpler.
Just a quick
review right there.
And this is important.
So this is going to be
applicable to treatments.
So things that they can
decrease the length
ventricle cavity. You don't
want to do that, but you
do want to do things that
can increase the left
ventricular cavity volume.
So, those will bring
the anterior micro
leaflet and septum
closer together, leading
to more obstruction. So,
if you have decreased
venous return,
decreased blood volume,
if you add, give them
positive inotropic drugs,
this promotes
obstruction. So what you
want to do is all of
these things, but avoid
very heavy exercise
and stay hydrated.
To increase that cavity volume,
things like increased venous
return, increased blood volume,
negative inotropic drugs.
And because this reduces
obstruction, so you
want to use the meds
and the ICDs if you need
them, avoid very heavy
exercise and stay
hydrated. Remember,
negative inotropic will help
your patients, as will
exercise and hydration,
limiting exercise.
So here's what you might
see in your clinic, and some
of the treatments, I
already mentioned it briefly
in the last slide, but
here's a little more detail.
Physical exam, it'll be
associated with an S4 heart
cell, so remember that,
that's through the left
atchia trying to contract
into a stiff left ventricle.
With outflow obstruction
you'll get a harsh systolic
ejection murmur,
crescendo decrescendo, and
it's best heard at the
left lower sternal border.
Screening, you want to
make sure you screen first
-degree relatives because of
the high degree of heredity.
Serial echocardiograms
because you
want to know how
it's increasing,
how the hypertrophy
is increasing. So all
of them should be, all
HCM patients should
be evaluated, even
if they don't have
symptoms because of
that sudden death risk.
Treatments, these are
medicines that are
commonly used and most
patients do well with
these medications
that relax the heart.
Okay.
Avoid strenuous exercise and
drugs that decrease preload.
For example,
alcohol can make you
dehydrated or strenuous
exercise, very strenuous
exercise can increase the
force of contraction. An
ICD may be implanted for
people at risk or sudden
death from dysrhythmias.
Some surgical techniques
that have to be used
for selected patients
may be myomectomy or
septal ablation, and
that's done with alcohol.
Here's a summary. It's
very simple, but it goes
over the main key points
and the effects that
can occur from hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy.
Thank you, and here is
the lecture feedback form.